A Finding Aid to the John Graham Papers, 1799-1988, bulk 1890-1961, in the Archives of American Art AAA.grahjohn
Archives of American Art
- Personal Business Records, circa 1931-1962; Series 3; 1.4 Linear feet Box 1-3
  Appointment books contain intermittent records of business and personal appointments from 1931 to 1938, and from 1948 to 1961. As with most of Graham's papers, they are heavily annotated and often contain sketches; a 1937 appointment book in particular contains numerous color drawings. Annotations range from notes about Graham's antique trade to personal matters and writings on Graham's wide-ranging interests. Some of these notes appear to have been made years after the year for which the book was made. One of the folders containing the address files is also annotated and illustrated. Notebooks found in the Writings series contain similar notes, writings, and sketches.
  Bank account records include check ledgers, deposit slips, and account statements. Financial notebooks consist of check ledgers that were re-used as notebooks, usually to keep track of antique objects and collectors. Additional notes related to antiques are found in financial notes, along with notes on personal assets and Graham's dealings with the Stable Gallery. Scattered drafts of letters are found among financial notes. Additional financial correspondence is also found filed with wills, stock records, and tax records.
  The book inventory and catalog of antiques and books are both annotated typescripts with notes in Graham's handwriting.
  Other details about the contents of folders are noted in the folder list.
  Additional correspondence related to Graham's business transactions can be found in Correspondence. In particular, letters related to Graham's estate can be found with Elinor Graham's correspondence.
  - Address Books, circa 1950-1961; 2 Folders (Box 1, Folder 84-85)
  - Address File, circa 1956-1961 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Appointment Book, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Appointment Book, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Appointment Book, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Appointment Book, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Appointment Book, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Appointment Book, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Appointment Book, 1948-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Appointment Book, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Appointment Book, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Appointment Book, 1951; undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Appointment Book, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Appointment Book, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Appointment Book, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Appointment Book, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Appointment Book, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Appointment Book, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Appointment Book, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Appointment Books, 1961; (2 volumes in 2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
  - Appointment Book, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Art and Antique Dealership, circa 1956-1960 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    (Contains receipts, accounts, contracts, lists, and correspondence)
  - Bank Account at Chase Manhattan Bank, 1957-1961; 6 Folders (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
  - Bank Account at Union Bank of Switzerland, 1958-1961; 3 Folders (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    not scanned
  - Book Inventory, circa 1946-1955 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - "Catalog of Antiques and Books for Insurance Purposes,", 1942-1952; 2 Folders (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Financial Notebook, 1957-1959 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Financial Notebook, 1959-1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Financial Notes, circa 1955-1961 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Stocks and Taxes, 1957-1961; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Travel Receipts, circa 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Wills and Estate of John Graham, circa 1954-1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Wills, Estate, and Trust of Marianne Strate Graham, circa 1954-1960 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1839; circa 1923-1986; Series 4; 2.9 Linear feet Box 3-5, OV 13
  This series contains writings by Graham and others in the form of book-length manuscripts, annotated books, card files, essays, lists, notes, notebooks, poetry, and handwritten prayers. Books and notebooks comprise the bulk of materials.
  Books are generally found in multiple drafts in the form of manuscripts and annotated typescripts. Two works are published books containing Graham's annotations: a 1923 book of poems, Have It, and Graham's most well-known work, Systems and Dialectics of Art, published in 1937. Another published work found here in manuscript form is a catalog of African art Graham created with Frank Crowninshield.
  The remaining manuscripts include a comparative history of art, some of which appears to have been incorporated into Systems and Dialectics of Art; a stylized, often abstract autobiographical work usually entitled Muerte Kalaka y Casa Nada (Child-hood) (Child Within), which has sometimes been referred to as Childhood in the literature on Graham; and a large collection of brief, alphabetically-arranged essays, which appear to have been worked on over the course of decades under various titles including Don Giovanni, Finale I-V, and Orifizio Mundi. Dates, format, and the text of these works overlap significantly, and appear to have been incorporated into one another in different versions at various stages of the writing. Manuscripts in this series have been filed according to titles found on the works or on binders containing the works, and dated according to scattered postmarks and dated items found among the papers. Card files contain handwritten versions of the same essays that appear in Orifizio Mundi and were likely preliminary to the typed manuscripts. Additional notes describing the various versions of book manuscripts are found in the folder list.
  Essays by Graham include typescripts, usually annotated, of published essays by Graham. Essays about Graham include photocopied typescripts of two essays written after his death. For additional published essays and articles about Graham, see Printed Materials.
  Lists are found on a wide range of subjects, often banal or personal and sometimes cryptic. For lists of artwork or other assets, see Correspondence and Personal Business Records.
  Miscellaneous notes and writings consist of notes, musings, essays, and aphorisms written or copied by Graham on a variety of subjects. Graham often applied brief titles to these apparently spontaneous writings, and where possible such items have been grouped together under his headings or other obvious subject matter. The folder entitled "Psychoanalysis" contains a lengthy, handwritten self-analysis dated from May through July of 1939. Miscellaneous notes and writings without titles or obvious subject matter are filed chronologically.
  Notebooks contain sketches, symbols, essays, and notes and are written in multiple languages and scripts, including Russian, Latin, Greek, French, and English. Some notebooks are written in appointment books, but do not seem to record any information specific to dates. Any appointment books Graham used to actually record appointments are filed with Personal Business Records, although they may also contain notes, essays, and sketches.
  Poetry includes poems by Graham, many of which are written in Russian, and poems about Graham, including one by the French poet Fernand Marc.
  Additional writings are found throughout the collection, notably in Personal Business Records, Printed Materials, and Artwork.
  - Books (Box 3)
    - African Art, circa 1937; 2 Folders (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
      (a catalog, in collaboration with Frank Crowninshield; multiple drafts interfiled)
    - Comparative History of Art, Typescript 1, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Comparative History of Art, Tyepscript 2, 1930; 2 Folders (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Comparative History of Art; Charts, Notes, and Plans, 1930; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
      see also OV 13
      (contains binder with heading "systems and dialectics of art," but the material within the binder appears to be for this art history work, versions of which bear the date 1930)
    - Don Giovanni Manuscript, circa 1949-1954; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 19-22)
    - Don Giovanni Typescript, circa 1954; 3 Folders (Box 3, Folder 23-25)
    - Finale I, circa 1936-1959; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 26-29)
      (titles with roman numerals for the Finale manuscripts taken from binders created by Graham; Finale I, II, and V appear to comprise a continuous typescript; Finale IV appears complete but is much shorter than other versions; Finale I contains front matter and alphabetically arranged entries from Abracadabra to Justice)
    - Finale II, circa 1936-1959; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 30-33)
      (contains entries from Kaligula to Russian Alphabet)
    - Finale III, circa 1936-1959; 5 Folders (Box 3, Folder 34-38)
      (contains original binder with drawing and entries from Circumference to Morning)
    - Finale IV, circa 1936-1959; 3 Folders (Box 3, Folder 39-41)
      (contains Preface and entries from Ages to Zodiac, and a copy of Graham's article "The Case of Mr. Picasso and Modern Art;" may be a compressed version of this work)
    - Finale V, circa 1936-1959; 3 Folders (Box 3, Folder 42-44)
      ( Finale V appears to be a continuation of Finale I and II; contains alphabetical entries from Sages to Youth, plus a summary of the work and an Index of all entries)
    - Have It, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      (Poems; author's annotated copy)
    - Muerte-Kalaka y Casi Nada (Child-Hood) (Child Within) Manuscript, circa 1936-1949; 4 Folders (Box 3, Folder 46-49)
    - Muerte-Kalaka y Casi Nada (Child-Hood) (Child Within) Original Typescript, circa 1936-1949; 3 Folders (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
    - Muerte-Kalaka y Casi Nada (Child-Hood) (Child Within) Typescript Copy 1, circa 1936-1949; 4 Folders (Box 4, Folder 4-7)
      (typescript copies 1 and 2 appear to be two carbon copies of original typescript, each with a different set of annotations)
    - Muerte-Kalaka y Casi Nada (Child-Hood) (Child Within) Typescript Copy 2, circa 1936-1949; 4 Folders (Box 4, Folder 8-11)
    - Muerte-Kalaka y Casi Nada (Child-Hood) (Child Within), Notes and Draft Fragments, circa 1936-1949; 3 Folders (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
    - Orifizio Mundi Volume II, circa 1936-1959; 6 Folders (Box 4, Folder 15-20)
      (carbon typescript of same text that appears in the Finale series, with fewer annotations; alphabetical order has been disturbed; there is no indication of a Volume I among the papers)
    - System and Dialectics of Art, undated; 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      (author's annotated copy; annotations appear to have been made in 1938 to the published 1937 work; later inscribed to Linda, presumably Leyden, who he met in 1959)
  - Card Files 1 and 2, undated (Box 4, Folder 22-24)
    2 shoeboxes of 3x5 inch cards and 1 folder of larger items removed from boxes; not scanned
    (handwritten entries with same text as Orifizio Mundi and Finale typescripts, arranged in two separate card files; in the first set of cards, the alphabetical order has been disrupted)
  - Essays by Graham (Box 5)
    - "Art", circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - "Autoportrait", circa 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - "Carlos Merida the Modern Painter of Mexico", undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - "The Case of Mr. Picasso", circa 1946 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - "Mexican Art Exhibition", circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - "Mexico", circa 1938 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - "Primitive Art and Picasso, circa 1937 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Essays about Graham (Box 5)
    - Forward to Second Edition of System and Dialectics of Art by Dorothy Dehner, circa 1971 (Box 5, Folder 8)
      Photocopy of annotated typescript
    - "John Graham" by Eilan Kokkinen, undated; circa 1968 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      three chapters of annotated typescript version of biography
  - Lists, circa 1958-1961 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, circa 1941-1961; 8 Folders (Box 5, Folder 11-18)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings by Subject (Box 5)
    - Art, 1961; undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Autobiographical, undated (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Autoportrait, circa 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Childhood, 1938; undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Comparative Languages, circa 1939-1950 (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Mexico, circa 1936-1939 (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Occult, undated (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Psychoanalysis, circa 1934-1939 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Science, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Society and Socialism, undated (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Travel, circa 1938-1961; 2 Folders (Box 5, Folder 29-30)
    - Yoga, circa 1955-1961 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Notebook, 1931 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Notebook, undated; 1939 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Notebook, 1839; undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
    (antique book with inscription dated 1839 re-used as notebook circa 1943)
  - Notebook, 1947-1953 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Notebook, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Notebook, circa 1948 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Notebook, 1949 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Notebooks, 1953; (3 volumes in 3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 39-41)
  - Notebook, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Notebook, circa 1959 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Notebook, 1959-1960 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Notebook, 1960 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Notebook, 1960-1961 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Notebook, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Notebooks, undated; (2 volumes in 2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 48-49)
  - Poems, 1915; 1976; 1953; undated (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Prayers, undated; 1944 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Oversized Writings (See Box 3, folder 15) (Box 13 (OV))
- Printed Materials, circa 1885-1961; Series 5; 3.7 Linear feet Boxes 6-9, OV 14
  This series contains published books, clippings, exhibition catalogs, pamphlets, brochures, publicity, reproductions of works of art, and sheet music collected by Graham and his family members.
  Books are filed by subject, and some are extensively annotated, especially those in the categories of Children's Books (inscribed by Graham to his son); Literature; Occult, Theosophy, and Religion; and Yoga. Books on Literature also have drawings on their endpages. These include works by Andrei Biely, Nikolai Gogol, Alexander Pushkin, Alexander Griboyedov, and an anthology of 20th century Russian poetry published in 1920. A 1922 book of criticism on Vladimir Mayakovsky features cover art by El Lissitzky. A single, unmarked copy of Graham's major published work of art theory, Systems and Dialectics of Art, is filed at the end of this series. See Writings for the author's annotated copy of this book and his book of poetry, Have It.
  Clippings are primarily about Graham, his family members, Elinor and David Graham, and friends. Also found is a 1938 article written by Graham entitled "Mexico." Clippings are in chronological order. Many clippings on subjects other than Graham are found in the reference files.
  Exhibition catalogs are for one-man shows or group shows featuring Graham's artwork, with scattered catalogs from other artists' exhibitions. Early catalogs contain essays on Graham by Duncan Phillips, Andre Salmon, David Burliuk, and Waldemar George. Catalogs of the Stable Gallery (1953-1954) are heavily annotated by Graham.
  Reference files include clippings, brochures, mimeos, publicity, pamphlets, postcards, maps, and other ephemera. Several of the files are primarily image files, and others contain articles or brochures. Some, such as the file on Picasso, contain both images and articles. Files occasionally contain Photostat copies of printed materials from a variety of sources. Materials in reference files are occasionally annotated.
  Sheet music includes mostly published piano arrangements, many of which are in Russian. A few handwritten scores are also found.
  Additional printed materials are found in Biographical Materials.
  Arrangement note
  The bulk of the material in this series has been scanned. Books have not been scanned in their entirety, but book covers, title pages, and annotated pages have been scanned.
  - Books (Box 6)
    - Antiques and Architecture, 1937-1960; 7 Folders (Box 6, Folder 1-7)
    - Calligraphy, undated; circa 1861; 2 Folders (Box 6, Folder 8-9)
    - Children's Books, undated; 1929-1934; 4 Folders (Box 6, Folder 10-13)
      (Books are inscribed to David Graham from John Graham and often annotated)
    - Health, circa 1955; 2 Folders (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
    - Literature, 1920-1959; undated; 7 Folders (Box 6, Folder 16-22)
      (Mostly in Russian; Drawings by Graham are found on covers and endpages)
    - Music, 1942; 1959-1960; 2 Folders (Box 6, Folder 23-24)
    - Occult, Theosophy, and Religion, 1926-1960; 22 Folders (Box 7, Folder 1-22)
    - Occult, Theosophy, and Religion, 1960; undated; 4 Folders (Box 8, Folder 1-4)
    - Travel, undated; 2 Folders (Box 8, Folder 5-6)
    - Yoga, 1949-1958; 4 Folders (Box 8, Folder 7-10)
    - Miscellaneous Books, 1902-1960; 5 Folders (Box 8, Folder 11-15)
  - Clippings, circa 1926-1988 (Box 8, Folder 16-19)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, circa 1920-1986 (Box 8, Folder 20-23)
  - Reference Files (Box 9)
    - Antiques and Architecture, circa 1939-1961 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Comparative Cultures, circa 1945-1960 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Health, circa 1958-1960; 4 Folders (Box 9, Folder 3-6)
      see also OV 14
    - History, circa 1961; undated; 2 Folders (Box 9, Folder 7-8)
    - Horses, undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
      See also OV 14
    - Miscellaneous Imagery, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Nineteenth and Early Twentiesth Century Art, undated; 1960 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Occult, Theosophy, and Religion, circa 1931-1960; 2 Folders (Box 9, Folder 12-13)
    - Old Masters, undated (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Picasso, undated; 1939 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Primitive Art, undated (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Psychoanalysis, circa 1938-1958 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Russian Nobility, undated (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Stocks, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - Theater and Actors, 1901-1960 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - Travel, circa 1956-1961 (Box 9, Folder 21-22)
    - Women, circa 1954-1961 (Box 9, Folder 23)
  - Sheet Music, circa 1885-1935 (Box 9, Folder 24)
  - System and Dialectics of Art, 1937 (Box 9, Folder 25)
    (see Writings for author's annotated copy)
  - Oversized Printed Materials (See Box 9, folders 4, 5, 7, 9, 11, 12, 14, 16, 20, 23, 24) (Box 14 (OV))
- Photographs, circa 1860-1985; Series 6; 0.9 Linear feet Box 9-10, 17, OV 15
  This series contains photographs of John Graham, his family and associates, artwork by Graham, European art and architecture, and antiques and primitive art.
  Photographs of John Graham date back to his childhood in Russia. Early photographs include several cabinet card portraits, one of which is unidentified but appears to be Graham at age two around 1888. Snapshots and formal portraits of Graham are found spanning his entire life. Some snapshots also depict his son, David Graham, in the early 1930s. The earliest group photograph present appears to depict Graham and his first wife Ebrenia. Other individuals in group photographs in which Graham appears are unidentified.
  Family photographs depict Graham's parents, wives, and children. Numerous photographs of the family of Elinor Gibson Graham, John Graham's fourth wife, are also found, including her father, Archer Gibson, a well-known organist, and the instruments he helped to design. Additional photographs of Graham's family members may be among the unidentified photographs filed under "Miscellaneous People."
  Other photographs in this series depict Picasso with Marie Vassilieff and Pâcquerette, Arshile Gorky with Graham; Françoise Gilot with Picasso and her children, Claude and Paloma; and Linda Leyden, a young girlfriend of Graham's in his later years. Also found are portraits of young women and men. It is likely that these depict actors or other famous figures.
  A group of photographic enlargements grouped together in this series appear to have been used by Graham in his creative process. Many of the originals from which the enlargements were derived are found among Graham's papers.
  Among the photographs of works of art are installation views, the earliest of which appear to be wall decorations or murals, and may be those Graham painted at Wells College around 1930. Other exhibitions shown include a Carnegie Institute show, a 1946 window display at Arnold Constable department store in New York City, and a 1985 exhibit at the Andre Emmerich Gallery, also in New York.
  Except for installation views, most of the photographs of works of art have not been scanned. Additional photographs are found in Biographical Materials and Correspondence.
  - John Graham (Box 9)
    - Formal Portraits and Passport Photos, circa 1888-1961; (3 folders, including copies) (Box 9, Folder 26-28)
    - Snapshots, circa 1915-1959; (3 folders, including copies) (Box 9, Folder 29-31)
    - Group Photographs, circa 1912-1949 (Box 9, Folder 32)
  - Family (Box 9)
    - Parents, circa 1880-1910 (Box 9, Folder 33)
    - Ebrenia (a.k.a. Catherine) Ignatevnia Makavelia, Kyril, and Maria, circa 1912-1945 (Box 9, Folder 34)
      (First wife and children)
    - Vera Aleksandrovna and Nicholas, circa 1918-1960 (Box 9, Folder 35)
      (Second wife and son)
    - Elinor Gibson Graham and David, circa 1905-1980; 3 Folders (Box 9, Folder 36-38)
      see also OV 15
      (Third wife and son)
    - David Graham, circa 1929-1960; 3 Folders (Box 9, Folder 39-41)
      (Son; for photographs of John and David Graham together, see John Graham Snapshots)
    - Frances Bryant and Archer Gibson, circa 1900-1950 (Box 9, Folder 42)
      (Parents of Elinor Gibson Graham)
    - Constance Wellman, circa 1936-1940 (Box 9, Folder 43)
      (Fourth wife)
    - Marianne Strate, circa 1930-1955 (Box 9, Folder 44)
      (Fifth wife)
  - Arshile Gorky with John Graham, circa 1930-1939 (Box 9, Folder 45)
  - Françoise Gilot and Children (Claude and Paloma Picasso), circa 1942-1960 (Box 9, Folder 46)
  - Linda Leyden, circa 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 47)
  - Pablo Picasso, circa 1916; undated (Box 9, Folder 48)
    (pictured with Françoise Gilot, Pâcquerette, and Marie Vassilieff)
  - Miscellaneous People, Identified or Dated, circa 1893-1945 (Box 9, Folder 49)
  - Miscellaneous People, Unidentified, circa 1860-1960; 2 Folders (Box 9, Folder 50-51)
  - Miscellaneous Places, circa 1920-1985 (Box 9, Folder 52)
  - Photographic Enlargements of Photos and Printed Materials, undated (Box 9, Folder 53)
    See OV 15
  - Photographs of Works of Art (Box 9)
    - by John Graham, Installation Views, 1945-1946; circa 1932; 1985 (Box 9, Folder 54)
    - by John Graham, Paintings (circa 1925-1946), undated; (2 of 4 folders) (Box 9, Folder 55-56)
    - by John Graham, Paintings (circa 1925-1946), undated; (2 of 4 folders) (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
    - by John Graham, Sketchbooks and Drawings, circa 1980, 1985, 6 Folders (Box 10, Folder 3-8)
    - Antiques and Primitive Art, undated (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - by Elinor Graham, undated (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - by Old Masters, undated (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Postcards of European Architecture and Sculpture, undated; 2 Folders (Box 10, Folder 12-13)
  - Portraits, circa 1880-1910; 8 Folders (Box 17, Folder 3-10)
    (Probably Actors and Actresses)
  - Portraits, Unidentified, circa 1880-1910; 2 Folders (Box 17, Folder 11-12)
  - Equestrian Statues and Studies, circa 1920 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Postcards, Gardens and Outdoor Sculpture, circa 1920s-1930s; 2 Folders (Box 17, Folder 14-15)
  - Postcards, Works of Art, by Others, circa 1920s (Box 17, Folder 16)
  - Oversized Photographs (See Box 9, folder 37, 51, 53, and Box 10, folder 11) (Box 15 (OV))
- Artwork, circa 1852-1961; Series 7; 1 Linear feet Box 10, OV 16
  This series includes sketchbooks, loose sketches and drawings, illustrated and annotated folders and envelopes, and artwork by artists other than John Graham in the form of drawings, prints, printed cloth, and a silhouette of Graham's daughter, Maria Dombrowski.